<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Jacob_Letter> 
    <Greeting>DEAR MR.GARRISON</Greeting>

    <pb p="2"/> 
    I thank you for the request of a line on the condition of the <person type="fugitive">contrabands</person>contrabands, and what I have seen while among them. When we parted at that pleasant gathering of the <person type="Quarkers">Progressive Friends</person> at <location state="Pennsylvania">Longwood</location>, you to return to the <location nickname="Massachusetts">Old Bay State</location>, to battle for <ideal>freedom</ideal> and <ideal>justice</ideal> to the <person type="unfree">slave</person>, I to go to the <location type="USCaptial">District of Columbia</location>, where the shackles had just fallen, I hoped that the glorious echo from the blow had aroused the spirit of <ideal>freedom</ideal>, if a spark slumbered in its bosom. Having purchased my ticket through to <city type="USCaptial">Washington</city> at the <city statee="Pennsylvania">Philadelphia</city> station, I reached the capital without molestation. Next morning, I went to <location type="USCaptial" use ="housing">Duff Green's Row</location>, Government head- quarters for the <person type="fugitive">contrabands</person> here. I found <gender type="male">men</gender>, <gender type="female">women</gender> and children all huddled together, without any distinction or regard to age or sex. Some of them were in the most pitiable condition. Many were sick with <disease>measles</disease>, <disease>diptheria</disease>, <disease>scarlet and typhoid fever</disease>. Some had a few filthy rags to lie on; others had nothing but the bare floor for a couch.There seemed to be no established rules among them; they were coming in at all hours, often through the night, in large numbers, and the <person type="overseer">Superintendent</person> had enough to occupy his time in taking the names of those who came in, and of those who were sent out. His office was thronged through the day by persons who came to hire these poor creatures, who they say will not work and take care of themselves. Single <gender type="female">women</gender> hire at <money quanity="four" unit="dollars">four dollars</money> a <time quanity="30Days">month</time>; a <gender type="female">woman</gender> with one child, <money quanity="2 1/2" unit="dollars">two and a half</money> or <money quanity="three" unit="dollars">three dollars</money> a <time quanity="30Days">month</time>. <gender type="male">Men's</gender> wages are <money quanity="ten" unit="dollars">ten dollars</money> per <time quanity="30Days">month</time>. Many of them, accustomed as they have been to <work type="manual">field labor</work>, and to living almost entirely out of doors, suffer much from the confinement in this crowded building. The little children pine like prison birds for their native element. It is almost impossible to keep the building in a healthy condition. Each day brings its fresh additions of the hungry, naked and sick.In the early part of <date year="1862">June</date>, there were, some days, as many as <quanity>ten</quanity> deaths reported at this place in <time quanity="24" unit="hours">twenty-four hours</time>.At this time, there was no matron in the house, and nothing at hand to administer to the comfort of the sick and dying. I felt that their sufferings must be unknown to the people. I did not meet kindly, sympathizing people, trying to soothe the last agonies of death. Those tearful eyes often looked up to me with the language, "Is this <ideal>freedom</ideal>?"

<pb p="2"/> 
    A new <person type="overseer">Superintendent</person> was engaged, <name type="Superintendent">Mr. Nichol</name>, who seemed to understand what these people most needed. He laid down rules, went to work in earnest pulling down partitions to enlarge the rooms, that he might establish two hospitals, one for the men and another for the women. This accomplished, cots and mattresses were needed. There is a small society in <city type="USCaptial">Washington</city>—<person type="society">the Freedman's Association</person>—who are doing all they can; but remember, <city type="USCapital">Washington</city> is not <location>New England</location>. I often met <person type="ChurchOfficial">Rev. W. H. Channing</person>, whose hands and heart are earnestly in the cause of the enslaved of his country. This gentleman was always ready to act in their behalf. Through these friends, an order was obtained from <person type="MilitaryOffical">Gen. Wadsworth</person> for cots for the <person type="fugitive">contraband</person> <building type="medicial">hospitals</building>.

<pb p="2"/>
    
    At this time, I met in <location type="USCaptial" use ="housing">Duff Green Row</location>, <name type="lady">Miss Hannah Stevenson</name>, of <lcity type="Massachusetts">Boston</lcity>, and <name type="lady">Miss Kendall</name>. The names of these ladies need no comment. They were the first <race>white</race> <gender>females</gender> whom I had seen among these poor creatures, except those who had come in to hire them. These noble ladies had come to work, and their names will be lisped in prayer by many a dying <person type="unfree">slave</person>. Hoping to help a little in the good work they had begun, I wrote to a lady in <city state="NewYork">New York</city>, a true and tried friend of the <person type="unfree">slave</person>, who from the first moment had responded to every call of humanity. This letter was to ask for such articles as would make comfortable the <condition type="unwell">sick</condition> and <condition>dying</condition> in the <building type="medicial">hospital</building>. On the <day type="weekend">Saturday</day> following, the cots were put up. A few hours after, an immense box was received from <city state="NewYork">New York</city>. Before the sun went down, those ladies who have labored so hard for the comfort of these people had the satisfaction of seeing every <gender type="male">man</gender>, <gender type="female">woman</gender> and <age type="young">child</age> with clean garments, lying in a clean bed. What a contrast! They seemed different beings. Every countenance beamed with <emotion type="happiness">gratitude</emotion> and satisfied rest. To me, it was a picture of holy peace within. The next day was the first Christian <date day="Sunday">Sabbath</date> they had ever known. One mother passed away as the setting sun threw its last rays across her dying bed, and as I looked upon her, I could but say—"One day of <ideal>freedom</ideal>, and gone to her God." Before the dawn, others were laid beside her. It was a comfort to know that some effort had been made to soothe their dying pillows. Still, there were other places in which I felt, if possible, more interest, where the poor creatures seemed so far removed from the immediate <emotion>sympathy</emotion> of those who would help them. These were the <person type="fugitive">contrabands</person> in <city stae="Virginia">Alexandria</city>. This place is strongly secesh; the inhabitants are kept quiet only at the point of Northern <weapon type="knife">bayonets</weapon>. In this place, the <person type="fugitive">contrabands</person> are distributed more over the city. In visiting those places, I had the assistance of two kind friends, <gender type="female">women</gender>. True at heart, they felt the wrongs and degradation of their race. These <gender type="female">ladies</gender> were always ready to aid me, as far as lay in their power. To <name type="lady">Mrs. Brown</name>, of <location type="StreetAddress" area="USCaptial">3d street, Washingto</location>n, and <name type="lady">Mrs. Dagans</name>, of <city state="Virginia">Alexandria</city>, the <person type="fugitive">contrabands</person> owe much <emotion type="happiness">gratitude</emotion> for the kindly aid they gave me in serving them. In this place, the <gender type="male">men</gender> live in an old foundry, which does not afford protection from the weather. The <condition type="unwell">sick</condition> lay on boards on the ground floor; some, through the kindness of the <person type="military">soldiers</person>, have an old blanket. I did not hear a complaint among them. They said it was much better than it had been. All expressed a willingness to work, and were <emotion type="nervous">anxious</emotion> to know what was to be done with them after the work was done. All of them said they had not received payment for their work and some wanted to know if I thought it would be paid to their masters. One old man said, "I don't kere if dey don't pay, so dey give me <ideal>freedom</ideal>. I bin working for ole maas all de time; he nebber gib me <money quanity="five" unit="cents">five cent</money>. I like de <PolitcalPower>Unions</PolitcalPower> fuss rate. If de <PolitcalPower>Yankee Unions</PolitcalPower> didn't come long, I'd be working tu de ole place now." All said they had plenty to eat, but no clothing, and no money to buy any.

    <pb p="2"/>
    Another place, the old school-house in <city state="Virginia">Alexandria</city>, is the Government head-quarters for the <gender type="female">women</gender>. This I thought the most wretched of all the places. Any one who can find an apology for <condition type="UnpaidWork">slavery</condition> should visit this place, and learn its curse. Here you see them from <age>infancy</age> up to a <age quanity="100" unit="years">hundred years old</age>. What but the love of <ideal>freedom</ideal> could bring these old people hither? One old <gender type="male">man</gender>, who told me he was a <age quanity="100" unit="years">hundred</age>, said he had come to be free with his children. The journey proved too much for him. Each visit, I found him sitting in the same spot, under a shady tree, suffering from <disease>rheumatism</disease>. Unpacking a barrel, I found a large coat, which I thought would be so nice for the old man, that I carried it to him. I found him sitting in the same spot, with his head on his bosom. I stooped down to speak to him. Raising his head, I found him <condition>dying</condition>. I called his wife. The old woman, who seems in her second childhood, looked on as quietly as though we were placing him for a night's rest. In this house are scores of <gender type="female">women</gender> and children, with nothing to do, and nothing to do with. Their husbands are at work for the Government. Here they have food and shelter, but they cannot get work. The <person type="unfree">slaves</person> who come into <location type="USCaptial">Washington</location> from <state>Maryland</state> are sent here to protect them from the <law>Fugitive Slave Law</law>. These people are indebted to <person>Mr. Rufus Leighton</person>, formerly of <city state="Massachusetts">Boston</city>, for many comforts. But for their Northern friends, God pity them in their wretched and destitute condition! The <person type="overseer">Superintendent</person>, <name type="Superintendent">Mr. Clarke</name>, a <state>Pennsylvanian</state>, seems to feel much interest in them, and is certainly very kind. They told me they had confidence in him as a friend. That is much for a <person type="unfree">slave</person> to say.

    <pb p="2"/>
    From this place, I went to <building>Birch's slave-pen</building> in <city state="Virginia">Alexandria</city>. This place forms a singular contrast with what it was <time quanity="two" unit="years">two years</time> ago. The habitable part of the building is filled with <person type="fugitive">contrabands</person>, the old jail is filled with secesh prisoners—all within speaking distance of each other. Many a compliment is passed between them on the change in their positions. There is another house on <location type="StreetAddress">Cameron street</location>, which is filled with very destitute people. To these places I distributed large supplies of clothing, given me by the ladies of <city state="NewYork">New York</city>, <city state="Massachusetts">New Bedford</city>, and <city state="Massachusetts">Boston</city>. They have made many a desolate heart glad. They have clothed the <condition type="unclothed">naked</condition>, fed the <condition type="unfed">hungry</condition>. To them, God's promise is sufficient.

    <pb p="2"/>
    Let me tell you of another place, to which I always planned my last visit for the day. There was something about this house to make you forget that you came to it with a heavy heart. The little children you meet at this door bring up pleasant memories when you leave it; from the older ones you carry pleasant recollections. These were what the people call the more favored <person type="unfree">slaves</person>, and would boast of having lived in the first families in <location type="state">Virginia</location>. They certainly had reaped some advantage from the contact. It seemed by a miracle that they had all fallen together. They were intelligent, and some of the young <gender type="female">women</gender> and children beautiful. One young <gender type="female">girl</gender>, whose beauty I cannot describe, although its magnetism often drew me to her side, I loved to talk with, and look upon her sweet face, covered with blushes; besides, I wanted to learn her true position, but her gentle shyness I had to respect. One day, while trying to draw her out, a fine-looking woman, with all the pride of a mother, stepped forward, and said— "Madam, this young woman is my son's wife." It was a relief. I thanked God that this young creature had an arm to lean upon for protection. Here I looked upon <condition type="UnpaidWork">slavery</condition>, and felt the curse of their heritage was what is considered the best blood of <location type="state">Virginia</location>. On one of my visits here, I met a mother who had just arrived from <location type="state">Virginia</location>, bringing with her four daughters. Of course, they belonged to one of the first families. This <gender type="male">man's</gender> strong attachment to this <gender type="female">woman</gender> and her children caused her, with her children, to be locked up one month. She made her escape one day while her master had gone to learn the news from the <PoliticalPower>Union</PoliticalPower> army. She fled to the Northern army for <ideal>freedom</ideal> and protection. These people had earned for themselves many little comforts. Their houses had an inviting aspect. The clean floors, the clean white spreads on their cots, and the general tidiness throughout the building, convinced me they had done as well as any other race could have done, under the same circumstances.

    <pb p="2"/>
    Let me tell you of another place—<location city="Arlington" state="Virginia">Arlington Heights</location>. Every lady has heard of <person type="MilitaryOfficial">Gen. Lee's</person> beautiful residence, which has been so faithfully guarded by our Northern army. It looks as though the master had given his orders every morning. Not a tree around that house has fallen. About the forts and camps they have been compelled to use the axe. At the quarters, there are many <person type="fugitives">contrabands</person>. The <gender type="male">men</gender> are employed, and most of the <gender type="female">women</gender>. Here they have plenty of exercise in the open air, and seem very <emotion type="positive">happy</emotion>. Many of the regiments are stationed here. It is a delightful place for both the <person type="military">soldier</person> and the <person type="fugitive">contraband</person>. Looking around this place, and remembering what I had heard of the character of the <gender type="male">man</gender> who owned it before it passed into the hands of its present owner, I was much inclined to say, Although the wicked prosper for a season, the way of the transgressor is hard.

    <pb p="2"/>
    When in <location type="USCaptial">Washington</location> for the <time quanity="24Hours">day</time>, my morning visit would be up at <location type="USCaptial" use ="housing">Duff Green's Row</location>. My first business would be to look into a small room on the ground floor. This room was covered with lime. Here I would learn how many deaths had occurred in the last <time quanity="24" unit="hours">twenty-four hours</time>. <gender type="male">Men</gender>, <gender type="female">women</gender> and children lie here together, without a shadow of those rites which we give to our poorest dead. There they lie, in the filthy rags they wore from the plantation. Nobody seems to give it a thought. It is an every-day occurrence, and the scenes have become familiar. One morning, as I looked in, I saw lying there five children. By the side of them lay a young <gender type="male">man</gender>. He escaped, was taken back to <state>Virginia</state>, whipped nearly to death, escaped again the next night, dragged his body to <location type="USCaptial">Washington</location>, and died, literally cut to pieces. Around his feet I saw a rope; I could not see that put into the grave with him. Other cases similar to this came to my knowledge, but this I saw.

    <pb p="2"/>
    Amid all this sadness, we sometimes would hear a shout of joy. Some mother had come in, and found her long-lost child; some husband his wife. Brothers and sisters meet. Some, without knowing it, had lived years within <distance quanity="20" unit="miles">twenty miles</distance> of each other.

    <pb p="2"/>
    A word about the schools. It is pleasant to see that eager group of old and young, striving to learn their A, B, C, and Scripture sentences. Their great desire is to learn to read. While in the school-room, I could not but feel how much these young <gender type="female">women</gender> and children needed <gender>female</gender>teachers who could do something more than teach them their A, B, C. They need to be taught the right habits of living and the true principles of life.

    <pb p="2"/>
    My last visit intended for <city state="Virginia">Alexandria</city> was on <day type="weekend">Saturday</day>. I spent the day with them, and received showers of thanks for myself and the good ladies who had sent me; for I had been careful to impress upon them that these kind friends sent me, and that all that was given by me was from them. Just as I was on the point of leaving, I found a young <gender type="female">woman</gender>, with an infant, who had just been brought in. She lay in a <condition>dying</condition> condition, with nothing but a piece of an old <person type="military">soldier</person> coat under her head. Must I leave her in this condition? I could not beg in <city state="Virginia">Alexandria</city>. It was time for the last boat to leave for <location type="USCaptial">Washington</location>, and I promised to return in the morning. The <person type="overseer">Superintendent</person> said he would meet me at the landing. Early the next morning, <name type="lady">Mrs. Brown</name> and myself went on a begging expedition, and some old quilts were given us. <name type="Superindentent">Mr. Clarke</name> met us, and offered the use of his large Government wagon, with the horses and driver, for the day, and said he would accompany us, if agreeable. I was delighted, and felt I should spend a happy <date day="Sunday">Sabbath</date> in exploring <location>Dixie</location>, while the large bundles that I carried with me would help make others happy. After attending to the sick mother and child, we started for <location type="religious">Fairfax Seminary</location>. They send many of the convalescent <person type="military">soldiers</person> to this place. The houses are large, and the location is healthy. Many of the <person type="fugitive">contrabands</person> are here. Their condition is much better than that of those kept in the city. They soon gathered around <name type="Superintendent">Mr. Clarke</name>, and begged him to come back and be their boss. He said, "<gender type="male">Boys</gender>, I want you all to go to Hayti." They said, "You gwine wid us, <name type="Superintendent">Mr. Clarke</name>?" "No, I must stay here, and take care of the rest of the <gender type="male">boys</gender>." "Den, if you aint gwine, de Lord knows I aint a gwine." Some of them will tell <name>Uncle Abe</name> the same thing. <name type="Superintendent">Mr. Clarke</name> said they would do anything for him—seldom gave him any trouble. They spoke kindly of <name>Mr. Thomas</name>, who is constantly empoyed in supplying their wants, as far as he can. To the very old people at this place, I gave some clothing, returned to <city state="Virginia">Alexandria</city>, and bade all good bye. Begging me to come back, they promised to do all they could to help themselves. One old woman said—"Honey tink, when all get still, I kin go an fine de old place? Tink de <PoliticalPower>Union</PoliticalPower> 'stroy it? You can't get nothin on dis place. Down on de ole place, you can raise ebery ting. I ain't seen bacca since I bin here. Neber git a libin here, where de peoples eben buy pasly." This poor old <gender type="female">Union</gender> thought it was nice to live where tobacco grew, but it was dreadful to be compelled to buy a bunch of <herb>parsley</herb>. Here they have preaching once every <date day="Sunday">Sabbath</date>. They must have a season to sing and pray, and we need true faith in Christ to go among them and do our duty. How beautiful if is to find it among themselves! Do not say the <person type="unfree">slaves</person> take no interest in each other. Like other people, some of them are designedly selfish, some are ignorantly selfish. With the light and instruction you give them, you will see this selfishness disappear. Trust them, make them free, and give them the responsibility of caring for themselves, and they will soon learn to help each other. Some of them have been so degraded by <condition type="UnpaidWork">slavery</condition> that they do not know the usages of civilized life; they know little else than the handle of the <farm_tool>hoe</farm_tool>, the <farm_tool>plough</farm_tool>, the cotton pad, and the overseer's <weapon type="whip">lash</weapon>. Have patience with them. You have helped to make them what they are; teach them civilization. You owe it to them, and you will find them as apt to learn as any other people that come to you stupid from oppression. The <person type="AfricanAmericans">negroes'</person> strong attachment no one doubts; the only difficulty is, they have cherished it too strongly. Let me tell you of an instance among the <person type="fugitive">contrabands</person>. One day, while in the <building type="medicial">hospital</building>, a <gender type="female">woman</gender> came in to ask that she might take a little orphan child. The mother had just died, leaving two children, the eldest <age quanity="three" unit="years">three years</age> old. This <gender type="female">woman</gender> had five children in the house with her. In a few days, the number would be six. I said to this mother, "What can you do with this child, shut up here with your own? They are as many as you can attend to." She looked up with tears in her eyes, and said—"The child's mother was a stranger; none of her friends cum wid her from de ole place. I took one <gender type="male">boy</gender> down on de plantation; he is a big boy now, working mong de <PolitcalPower>Unions</PolitcalPower>. De Lord help me to bring up dat <gender type="male">boy</gender>, and he will help me to take care dis child. My husband work for de <PolitcalPower>Unions</PolitcalPower> when dey pay him. I can make home for all. Dis child shall hab part ob de crust." How few <race>white</race> mothers, living in luxury, with six children, could find room in her heart for a seventh, and that child a stranger!

    <pb p="2"/>
    In this house there are scores of children, too young to help themselves, from <age quanity="eight" unit="years">eight years</age> old down to the little <age quanity="one" unit="day">one-day</age> freeman, born at railroad speed, while the young mother was flying from <state>Virginia</state> to save her babe from breathing its tainted air.

    <pb p="2"/>
    I left the <person type="fugitive">contrabands</person>, feeling that the people were becoming more interested in their behalf, and much had been done to make their condition more comfortable. On my way home, I stopped a few days in <city state="Pennsylvania">Philadelphia</city>. I called on a lady who had sent a large supply to the <building type="medicial">hospital</building>, and told her of the many little orphans who needed a home. This lady advised me to call and see the <person>Lady Managers</person> of an institution for orphan children supported by those ladies. I did so, and they agreed to take the little orphans. They employed a gentleman to investigate the matter, and it was found impossible to bring them through <city state="Maryland">Baltimore</city>. This gentleman went to the captains of the propellers in <city state="Pennsylvania">Philadelphia</city>, and asked if those orphan children could have a passage on their boats. Oh no, it could not be; it would make an unpleasant feeling among the people! Some of those orphans have died since I left, but the number is constantly increasing. Many mothers, on leaving the plantations, pick up the little orphans, and bring them with their own children; but they cannot provide for them; they come very destitute themselves.

    <pb p="2"/>
To the ladies who have so nobly interested themselves in behalf of my much oppressed race, I feel the deepest debt of gratitude. Let me beg the reader's attention to these orphans. They are the innocent and helpless of God's poor. If you cannot take one, you can do much by contributing your mite to the institution that will open its doors to receive them.

    <Signature>LINDA.</Signature>
</Jacob_Letter>